# 去河裡面搞點螃蟹來吃哦
We're going to the riverside and catch some crabs.
# 你看這個是找兄弟借的
Look! These traps are borrowed from my,
# 找兄弟借的籠子
from my buddy.
# 把這個餌料放到放個地籠裡面去
Put the bait into the traps.
# 把這個籠子丟到河邊去 就有螃蟹會進來了
Drop the traps at the riverside and the crabs will be coming in.
# 好多魚呀這邊
A lot of fish here!
# 我要抓螃蟹 不要魚
But I want crabs, not fish.
# 把這個扔到這裡去
Let me drop this one here.
# 很多螃蟹的哦這裡
Here are a lot of crabs, you know.
# 一到 一到晚上很好螃蟹都出來活動
Once, once it gets dark, a lot of crabs will be coming out.
# 這裡可以放一個
One can be placed here.
# 哎呀
Aya!
# Look! Another one can be placed here, here.
# 你看 這裡可以放一個哦 這裡
Hang it onto the tree.
# 掛在這樹上
Then it won’t be blown away.
# 風就吹不走
Wa! Look! A crab is getting in very soon.
# 哇 你看有一個螃蟹 馬就就進去了
See? It’s coming here in a moment.
# 看到沒有 等下它就過來了
Here are a lot of small fish.
# 好多小魚啊這裡
Look! The crab, it’s searching around the trap. It doesn’t know where the entrance is.
# 你看 那個螃蟹 它在翻那個籠子 它不知道從哪裡進
It’s over there. How can you get the food otherwise? Eh? It’s going there now.
# 在那邊啊 不然怎麼吃的到哦 誒它馬上過去啦
Let’s see if it can reach that side. Aya! This crab is so clever.
# 看它能不能游過去 誒呀 好聰明吲這個螃蟹
It will get in right away.
# 馬上就進去啦
Almost there! Eh? It’s going back here.
# 再往前一點 誒 又倒回來啦
Stupid crab!
# 那麼笨
The function is right in the front. Go a bit further to the front!
# 前面就是路口啦 再往前走一點啊
It’s just crawling around, but never gets in.
# 它愣是不進 還老是爬來爬去
Go that side. A tiny little bit more, just a tiny little bit more!
# 過去 再爬過一點點 再一點點
Go a bit further!
# 再過來一點
It’s not going.
# 不過去
Place one here.
# 這裡放一個
Here must be something.
# 這裡肯定有東西
It’s really dangerous here.
DO NOT IMITATE
# 請勿模仿 (註︰警告字句)
# 這裡好危險哦
Drop one here.
# 這個放在這裡
I’ll drop another one up there.
# 上面再放一個
This one can be dropped here.
# 這個就放在這裡
All traps have now been placed. We’ll come to get them back tomorrow.
# 現在放好啦 明天過來收
Let’s see if there are any good snacks up there,
# 我去看一下上面有沒有好吃的
something like wild fruits.
# 野果啊之類的
It's really a scenic spot here.
# 這裡的風景很漂亮的哦
Look! It’s like beans. Who knows what it is.
# 你看 扁豆一樣的 不知道甚麼
I don’t think it’s edible.
# 應該是不能吃的哦
It has beans, you know.
# 有豆子的哦
There are beans inside.
# 裡面有豆子
But I have no ideas what plant it is.
# 我也不知道甚麼植物
Look! It’s really a scenic place, isn’t it?
# 你看 這裡的環境很漂亮吧
All are, this is, this is, the headwater of our village, this one.
# 全是 就是 就是 我們家鄉的水源哦 這個
This is the headwater.
# 這就是水源地
Look! These two,
# 你看 這兩個
tiny plums. They're so small.
# 小布丁 那麼小的
Are there any larger ones?
# 沒有大一點的
It’s now on my wish list. I’ll come and pick them right away next time.
# 先看好來 不次直接來摘
That’s so called “no frills”.
# 大家常說的直奔主題
Look! This tree is really big. It’s at least a hundred years old.
# 你看 這棵樹好大哦 最少有上百年的歷史哦
There are a couple of tree hollows. In the hollows, there must be,
# 還有幾個樹洞 榼洞裡面肯定有
either, either birds, or snakes.
# 要不是 要不就是鳥 要不就是蛇
Well, the path is blocked
# 好 路都被擋了
Look! This is shameplant.
# 你看 這個是含羞草哦
Look! It will shrink immediately if I blow to it.
# 沒反應 這個草肯定不要臉
No response. This plant must be shameless.
# 還含羞草 肯定是冒牌貨
How can it call itself shameplant? It’s counterfeit.
# 你看 這個 野果那些都還沒熟哦
Look! The, the wild fruits are not yet ripe.
# 我摘點這個蕉芋花來吸一下
Let me pick some Indian shots and suck them.
# 要秋天才熟
They won’t be ripe until autumn.
# 感覺那野果長的好慢啊
It seems that the wild fruits take such a long time to become ripe.
# 好 回家啦 回家啦 明天再來看
Alright! Let’s go, let’s go! Let’s come again tomorrow.
# 剛好路過攝影小哥家哦
It just so happens that we pass by Mr. Cameraman’s home.
# 你看 他家的板栗說他說不要啦
Look! These are his chestnuts but he says that he doesn’t want them anymore.
# 聽到這句話我就想笑
Hearing this makes my smile.
# 要砍掉的哦 過 過幾天就要砍掉啦
It needs to be cut away, you know. It, it will be cut away in a few days.
# 我把那板栗先把它弄下來再說
But before anything, let me get the chestnuts first.
# 一起上 哈哈 一起上
Let’s climb together. Haha! Climb together!
# 一起上也可以呀
Why not? Let's climb together.
# 來 哪[SIC]鋸子給我
C’mon! Give me the saw.
# 嗯 我拿給你
Um! Here you are.
# 請物模仿 (註︰警告字句)
DO NOT IMITATE
# 哎喲 有幾個
Ayo! Here are some!
# 你看 這多吧
Look! A lot, right?
# 這還有一個大的
Here’s also a big one.
# 怎麼這麼脆的這種樹
Why is this tree so brittle,
# 就這麼脆弱
so fragile?
# 等下 等下 我出來先
A moment, a moment. Let me get out first.
# 注意腳
Watch your legs!
# 拉著樹枝就可以啦
Just pull the branches.
# 你看 這個4胞胎喲
Look! These are quadruplets.
# 把板栗搞下來就行啦
We only need to take the chestnuts,
# 樹枝就不要啦
not the branches.
# 這個夠大吧
This is really big, isn’t it?
# 這板栗都是
These chestnuts are all,
# 很漂亮的哦 這種板栗
all very pretty, you know, these chestnuts.
# 你看 這一這一袋
Look! This, this bag,
# 跟這裡應該有五六十斤
together these, should be almost thirty kilograms.
# 帶瞉的哦
The shells are still there, you know.
# 回去挖一下應該挖得到 五六斤那個
After cracking them at home, we should be able to have about three kilograms of,
# 那個 那個板栗出來
I mean, I mean, chestnuts.
# 沒有啦 樹上還有好多啊
That’s all. There are still a lot on the tree.
# 留到下次來搞 不要一下子摘完啦
Leave them for next time. We’re not taking everything at a time.
# 細水長流
It’s called delayed gratification.
# 好啦 回去啦
Alright! Let’s go back!
# 今天晚上有得挖啦 挖一晚上
That’s our task this evening. It’s gonna take the whole evening.
# 有些板栗都烏啦
Some chestnuts have already turned dark.
# 有些就是還是白的
And some are still white.
# 你看 這種就很嫩的
Look! This is a very young one.
# 這很(好)吃的這個
It tastes really good.
# 那種 直接可以當那個水果 水果來吃
It’s like, it can be eaten right away as fruit.
# 黑了的就要用那個
The dark ones need to be,
# 蒸一下 蒸熟了 蒸熟了才可以吃 才好吃
to be steamed. They taste much better after being, being steamed.
# 那個烏的也可以吃 就是
The dark ones are still edible. They’re just,
# 就是太硬啦 不好吃 硬邦邦
just too hard, as hard as rock, don’t taste good.
# 好吃
Tasty!
# 有好多都是
Many people, like,
# 乾了再檢 就不用挖
they pick after the chestnuts are dried. Then there’s no need to crack them.
# 沒那麼好吃
But the taste is not comparable.
# 這個板栗太難挖啦
Cracking these chestnuts is really exhausting
# 讓它曬一下 讓它自然爆開
We leave them dry under the sun. They’re gonna crack open,
# 自然爆開來
by themselves, naturally.
# 你看 這兩個板栗好肥呀 看到沒
Look! These two chestnuts are really fat. See?
# 圓嘟嘟的看到沒有
They’re round and chubby. See?
# 這些都嫩的哦
These are really young,
# 很漂亮的哦
and pretty, you know.
# 再吃一個 這嫩的好好吃啊
Let me have one more. The young ones are really tasty.
# 而且它裡面的那個肉 也很甜
And the pulp inside, is also very sweet.
# 看到沒有 這個 表面這層保護膜
See? This one, the skin on the surface,
# 隨便一撕就撕得開來
can be very easily peeled off.
# 還很嫩 如果老了就不好吃啦
It’s still very young. It doesn’t taste good after getting old.
# 你看 這個
Look! This one
# 嗯
Um!
# 好香
It smells so good!
# 感覺不好剥
Cracking these chestnuts doesn’t seem easy.
# 剥那麼久才剥那麼一點
We’ve only done with such a little bit after such a long time.
# 第二天
The next day
# 你看 在這裡喲
Look! It’s here.
# 剛好今天來收 收一下這個地籠
We’re coming today, to get, get back the traps.
# 我們就邊叫hang
We say “hang” the traps in our dialect here.
# 意思就是收地籠
It means getting back the traps.
# 你看 肯定有螃蟹的
Look! There must be some crabs.
# 專抓螃蟹
They’re specially designed for crabs.
# 看一下有兩個 我看到有兩個
It seems to be two. I see two crabs.
# 哦 3個哦
Oh! Three, actually!
# 你看 一個大的 兩個那麼小的
Look! One is big, and two are so small.
# 哦 把它倒出來
Oh. I pour them out.
# 看 這裡還有一個哦
Look! Here’s another one.
# 這個有沒有
Are there any crabs?
# 也有幾個
Yea, some.
# 又一個小螃蟹
One more little crab
# 兩個
Two more
# 3個 但是有一個大的哦
Three! But one is big.
# 有4個哦 這個
Oh, four crabs here
# 看了 看了一眼
I peeped, peeped into it.
# 你看 這裡有4個
Look! Here are four crabs.
# 你看 兩個籠子就搞了那麼多
Look! We have so many crabs in just two traps.
# 你看一下其它的
Let me have a look at the rest.
# 現在已經7個啦
We have seven crabs now.
# 看一下前面 前面還有幾個看一下有沒少
Let’s have a look in the front. There are still some traps. Let’s see how many crabs there are.
# 你看
Look!
# 7個
Seven crabs.
# 看一下這個籠子有沒有
Let me see if there’s anything in this trap.
# 也有哦 也有螃蟹
Yea, there are crabs.
# 把它解開來
Let me untie it.
# 差點跑啦
It almost ran away.
# 看一下前面有沒有
Let me see if there are any more in the front.
# 就一個
Just one
# 這麼大的籠子就裝了一個
It's such a big trap but there's only one crab.
# 還一個那麼小的
And it's a tiny crab.
# 先把籠子放在這裡先 等下倒回來拿
I leave the trap here first. I’ll come back for it later.
# 我去那邊了
I’m going to that side.
# 那裡還有一個籠子
There’s one more trap.
# 這裡有點危險
It’s a bit dangerous here.
# 這個看一下有沒有啊
Let me see if there are any crabs.
# 不是吧 空軍
Are you kidding me? It’s empty!
# 一個都沒看到
I can’t see anything,
# 一個都沒有
Not even a single crab.
# 今天的收獲也不錯哇 有十多個
It’s a rather fruitful day today. We have a dozen of crabs.
# 回去
Let’s go back, and then,
# 用那個
fry,
# 油炸了 把它炸啦
fry them in oil.
# 金黃金黃色的 炸到來吃
Fry them. They’ll turn golden brown.
# 剛好今天菜又不用買了
So that means we don’t need to buy food today.
# 你看 螃蟹兄弟 今天就把你當菜吃啦
Look! Hey crabs, my buddies, you’ll be my dish today.
# 沒辦法 豬肉貴呀
I have no choice. Pork is expensive these days.
# 你看 今天中午就吃這個哦 就是開水
Look! This is our lunch today. This is boiling water.
# 要燙一下 表面的寄生蟲才會燙掉的
We gotta blanch them, to get rid of the parasites on the surface.
# 這個沒辦法
That’s the only way.
# 一下就變紅啦
They turn red immediately.
# 這樣燙一下它表面的那些
After being blanched, the tiny,
# 那些小小的那些寄生蟲就全部燙死掉
tiny parasites on the surface would all be killed.
# 這個生殖器官要拔掉 不要
The reproductive organ needs to be removed. We don’t want it.
# 這個
Nor,
# 蓋子也不要
nor the shells,
# 這個鰓也不要
nor the gill.
# 好 就這樣就可以啦
Alright! It's fine now.
# 這個是母的 這個是公的 你看
This is female, and this is male. Look!
# 你看 這個母的就這樣子的 公的就這樣子的
Look! This is how female looks like, and this is how male looks likes.
# 啊
Ah!
# 搞那麼緊
Why is it so tight?
# 不一樣的 一看就看很出來
They are very different. You can tell immediately.
# 洗乾淨來 處理好了就那麼一點
After cleaning, just a little bit remains.
# 那麼一點點
Just a tiny little bit.
# 螃蟹的肉太少啦 多加點生薑
The crabs don’t give much to eat. Let’s put more ginger,
# 看上去就多一點
so that it looks more plentiful.
# 加點鹽
Put some salt.
# 夠啦 加點醬油
Enough. Put some soy sauce.
# 加點料酒
Put some cooking wine
# 腌個十分鐘左右就下油鍋啦
Marinate it for ten minutes then we can put them into the wok.
# 加點油
Put some oil.
# 穿到衣服來
Let me put on my jacket.
# 蟹黃都出來啦
The guts are bursting out.
# 看 可以啦 熟啦
Look! Alright! It’s done now.
# 把它撈起來
Let me take them out.
# 大大小小
Big and small,
# 全部都是
all went,
# 一起下油鍋
into the same wok together.
# 就搞了那麼一點點
And became just a tiny little bit here.
# 也好 也是一道菜
Anyway. It’s still a dish.
# 嗯 有沒有孜然粉
Um? Any cummin powder?
# 咩 來 有吃的哦
Meh~~ C’mon! I have food here!
# 要不要
You want some?
# 羊的肚子好大啦
The goats have very big bellies now.
# 你看 上一分鐘它還在夾我哦
Look! They were still pinching me a minute ago.
# 下一分鐘就變成啦
A minute later, they became,
# 這個樣子
as you can see now,
# 變成了我的食物
became my food.
# 嗯 很不錯
Um! It’s really not bad.
# 好香啊
It smells so good!
# 好啦 今天的視頻就到這裡啦
Alright! The video ends here.